Stanford
University group velocity and phase
velocity okay good all right let's uh
let's talk about it a little bit
um generally the phase
velocity of a wave doesn't have anything
to do with measurable properties of uh
of the wave of or of
the measurable things in quantum
mechanics it's the group velocity which
is really
the velocity at which signals move the
velocity at which particles move and so
forth so let me just show you what's at
stake and what's going
on
um the first thing is if you have a
plain wave a s or a cosine or an e to
the I
KX and that's what just e to the I KX we
try e to the I
KX minus Omega
t or just signs the S of KX minus Omega
T will also do in fact let's just write
that sin of KX minus Omega
T looks like that and how does that wave
move how does the top of each Crest move
the top of each
Crest
moves uh in such a way that this thing
inside the sign is
constant in other words for example
right over here at time T equals 0 and
at x equals 0 the sine wave or the sine
wave is not a maximum at that point at x
equals 0 and T equals z the sine wave
happens to be over here okay but where
how where is the sign wave after a
certain amount of time T it's at the
place or that point here has moved it's
moveed to the place where KX minus Omega
T is equal to
zero okay where is that that's at the
position X is equal to Omega over K *
T just dividing by K now that's not too
surprising if you think about it for a
minute Omega is a frequency so it's
inverse to the period of oscillation to
the time of oscillation it's one over
the time of oscillation there's a two Pi
in there but the two pies appear in both
things so
Omega is like one over the period of the
wave one over T the amount of time that
it takes for the wave to oscillate and
K is like 1/ Lambda actually there are
two pies in these equations two pi's in
the numerator let's put them
in and so Omega over K what's Omega over
K Omega over K is Lambda over T it's the
wavelength divided by the period the
wavelength is the distance it moves in
one oscillation the period is the time
that it takes the ratio is the velocity
so this is the velocity of the peak of
each wave okay for a plain wave
so that's called the phase
velocity now let's think about shring a
waves for a minute shring a waves have a
connection between Omega and K it the
connection is to remember it all you
have to remember is that Omega is really
secretly energy and K is really secretly
momentum if we set H bar equal to one
and so using the formula that energy is
equal to momentum squ / mass that just
becomes Omega s is equal to k^2 / by 2
m I say momentum squ divid by mass over
twice the mass this is as usual with h
bar = Cal 1 in fact there's no C's in
this formula but there are some H bars
okay so that would tell you for example
let's compute the phase velocity the
phase velocity of a shring a wave for
shring a wave Omega sorry Omega is equal
to k^2 over 2m not omega s Omega is k^2
over 2 m so what is the group velocity
it's Omega / K Omega ided by K is equal
to K over 2
m that's the phase
velocity k / 2
m what's the velocity of a particle in
terms of its momentum and its
mass momentum divided by m there an
extra factor of two here what's that
doing there peculiar thing the phase uh
the phase velocity is not the velocity
of the motion of a classical particle
okay let's uh let's just keep that in
mind that's true but let's do something
else now supposing I add
a constant to the frequency of every
wave I simply take the frequency of
every wave all of them for okay and I
add the same constant what should I call
that constant um name for
it it's MC squar but let's not uh let's
not belor it's not important let's just
add a constant an overall constant to
the frequency of all waves what does
that do to the group veloc to the phase
velocity well it changes it Omega / K
will now have an extra term in it okay
it'll have an extra term in it and it
won't be the same whatever it does it
will be C over K it'll have an extra
term in it the phase velocity will have
changed but I tell you right now there
is no
physics in just adding a constant to the
frequency of every Schrodinger wave what
does it correspond to it corresponds to
adding a constant to the energy of a
particle and adding a numerical constant
to the energy doesn't ever change
anything only energy differences are
ever ever important all right can we see
what's going on in terms of the shringer
wave well a shringer field s is some
kind of sum or integral either sum or an
integral of creation operators
rather Annihilation operators in this
case uh e to the I
KX e to the minus I Omega T where Omega
is the
Omega which is related to K so let's
write Omega of
K now supposing I add to Omega just this
constant c what does it do it adds in or
multiplies into each one of these way
waves e to the i
c sorry e to the minus i
c all of the waves in here that make up
the shringer field all get multiplied by
the same time dependent phase here so
what it does is if you had a solution of
the Schrodinger equation and you added a
constant to the phase it would just
change the solution let's say s of X and
it would just multiply it by E to Theus
i c
t that's all it would do it would
multiply the wave Sorry
by I'm s of x and
t it would change the wave by
multiplying it by a Time dependent phase
all of the quantities of physical
interest that are made out of the
Schrodinger field involves s times its
complex
conjugate the probability density for
example is s Time s star all possible
expectation values quantum mechanical
expectation values always involve s
times its complex
conjugate so what happens to S times its
complex
conjugate when you perform this
operation it cancels out
it cancels out because s
star gets multiplied by E to plus I
CT and when you multiply them they
cancel out as a consequence there is no
physical
measurability to adding a constant to
all of the phases and nevertheless it
changes the
velocity of the shinger Waves so there
must be something about this change of
velocity which is well this change of
frequency which is not so much un let's
say for the phase velocity the phase
velocity is not something which is ever
measured when or ever appears when you
multiply s times s star so it's an
artifact of a
particular
mathematical
um set of conventions on the other hand
the group velocity really does mean
something it is the motion of the wave
the motion of it if you have a wave
packet uh which is centered in some
place in other words if you have a bunch
of waves which add up a bunch of waves
bunch of plain waves which add up to
something that looks like that maybe it
has some oscillations in it but which
look like a lump the whole lump moves
with a velocity that's called a group
velocity but let's see if we can see
just a little roughly wide
if you take a whole bunch of plain waves
every plane wave looks like this goes on
and on forever how is it possible to add
them up so that you get a concentrated
lump
someplace the answer is destructive
interference right destructive
interference so that the waves are in
phase and addir up over here and they're
out of phase and cancel over here so the
question then comes up if we're into
interested in the motion of waves and
how waves of slightly different
frequency reinforce each other and make
high points and low points that's let's
try to follow how that works let's take
two waves not a single wave but let's
take two waves of very neighboring
close M
momentum and try to follow where
the
reinforcing
um constructive interference takes place
that'll be good enough let's just
followw the constructive interference
takes place between the two waves so in
particular
take e to the I KX we could just take s
s is good enough s k
s KX minus Omega of
KT and let's add to it this is just a
wave moving along with momentum K energy
Omega and let's add to it another wave
which
is let's put parenthesis around
this
s k Prime where K Prime and K are very
close to each other
x minus Omega of K Prime
T where are they in phase and where are
they out of phase in Phase means they
reinforce each other out of phase and in
particular it'll mean that the two terms
here have the same sign and there are
other places where they'll have opposite
sign well one easy way to find out where
they reinforce each other is to ask when
is the argument argument meaning the
thing in the bracket here when is the
argument of this wave the same as the
argument of this wave those are the
places that in that case that particular
place where the argument of this wave
and the argument of this wave are the
same it's clear the waves will reinforce
each other okay they'll reinforce each
other and they will be uh in
constructive interference all right
where is that that's at the place where
K
xus Omega of K T is equal to K Prime
x minus Omega let's just call it Omega
Prime Omega Prime means Omega of K Prime
T okay but let's write this in the
following way K minus K
Prime
X is equal to Omega minus Omega Prime t
two neighboring waves will reinforce
each other along a
trajectory where x and t are related by
this
equation okay let's just divide it by K
minus K
Prime and now assume that K and K Prime
are very close to each other just for
Simplicity let's imagine
uh that uh they only differ by a very
small amount a small fractional amount
then what is Omega minus Omega Prime
over K minus K
Prime it's the derivative of Omega with
respect to
K that's all it is is derivative of
Omega with respect to K if Omega and
Omega Prime are near each other and so
what it says is the place where they
reinforce each other will travel along
an orbit which is
X is equal to the derivative of Omega
with respect to K let
right d Omega by
DK time
T this is also a
velocity it's the velocity of the place
where the waves reinforce each
other
okay and it's called the group velocity
it's the group velocity let's calculate
it if Omega is k^2 over 2 M plus an
arbitrary constant this is all right
this is the phase velocity the
phase what about the group velocity
that's the derivative of Omega with
respect to
K derivative of Omega with respect to K
that's equal to 2K / 2 m otherwise known
as K Over m
and what do we get from
here nothing
zilch okay this of course this is the
group velocity V
group notice two things the group
velocity does not depend on this extra
additive thing that I put into each
frequency number one and number two it's
exactly the velocity of a n relativistic
particle momentum divided by
mass okay
so the two went away yeah that's right
the two went away exactly when I
differentiated K I got 2 K ided by 2 m
and two and A8 so the group
velocity is the thing which is most
closely associated with the classical
motion of a particle it's also the only
thing that's associated with propagation
of signals and so forth not the phase
velocity we could go ahead a little more
with this let's see do we want
to when they speed light is C that phas
group okay both so let's uh let's go
through that let's go through that and
see why that's true this C here is not
the speed of light
incidentally right this see is not the
speed of light but let's go through that
let's take a relativistic wave and
calculate both the group and phase
velocity all right for that we need to
know a fact or two we need to know the
relationship between we need to start
with the relationship between energy and
momentum does does any of this have
anything to do sometimes they talk about
light going faster than the speed light
no no it doesn't it doesn't it doesn't
it doesn't it doesn't it's a good it's
it's it is a good
question uh but it doesn't have to do
with that it's a separate issue yeah
could he be thinking of you know the
classic a wave guide the phase velocity
is always greater than the speed of
light the group velocity is always less
the product is the speed of light yeah
let's uh all so let me give you an
example of that happening right now
um not for a wave guide with a uh uh
yeah it is a wave no not a wave guide
just a a wave equation for a particle
with a mass um we begin we begin in
order to in order to figure out the
relation the wave equation is nothing
but the relation between Omega and K the
hell with a wave equation just the
relation between Omega and K for a
relativistic particle particle moving
close to but not at the speed of light
it's got a mass it's got a mass if it
didn't have a mass it would move with a
speed of light okay what's the
connection
Omega is energy let's write it first in
a form that we might remember best
what's the relation between energy and
momentum for a particle which is
relativistic
remember
uh uh relation with
momentum
p square
root okay square root of p^2 + M2 but uh
do we want to put the speeds of light
into here I think there's a c to the 4th
and a c^2 but let's set c equal to one
yeah we've already set c equal to one uh
later on we can put back the uh uh the
C's if we want to it's it's not
necessary here's the energy and if we
now set H bar equal to 1 this is exactly
the same as writing Omega is equal to
square < TK of k^2 plus m^2 so for a
relativistic wave a relativistic
particle the frequency is the square
root of K2 + M2 now if M happens to be
equal to zero then it's Omega equals the
magnitude of
K apart from a speed of light which I
set equal to one that's the relationship
for a wave moving with a speed of light
that Omega is equal to K what's the
group velocity what's what first of all
what's the phase
velocity the phase velocity is Omega
over K right
V phase is Omega over K and that's one
what does that mean one speed of light
right what about the group velocity V
group that's the derivative of Omega
with respect to K what is
that
one the group velocity and the phase
velocity are the same for a
wave with mass equal to zero
all right so if the forget that this is
mass this is just a yeah it is mass of
course it's Mass uh energy equal sare
root of momentum square plus Mass squ
all right but now let's calculate the
group velocity when the mass is not
equal to zero well both of them let's
calculate both of them Omega over K
that's the phase velocity that's the
square root of k^2 +
m^2 over K but let's put it all inside
the square root let's put it all inside
the square root then it becomes k^2 +
m^2 over
k^2 is this bigger than or smaller than
one bigger than one k^2 plus m^2 over
k^2 is bigger than 1 so the phase
velocity Omega over K is bigger than one
bigger than the speed of light okay uh
oh you get a little bit scared waves
moving faster than the speed of light
but what about the phase velocity let's
work that
out ah group velocity thank you the
group velocity is the derivative of
Omega with respect to K all right what's
the derivative of Omega with respect to
K oops not t the Omega
DK all right we have to take the
derivative of a square root that gives
us 1/ twice the square root
of k^2 + m^2 and then we have to
differentiate the argument here with
respect to K so that just gives us K it
gives us K over this this is the
derivative which is also equal to square
< TK of k^2 over k^2 +
m^2 isn't that nice the group
velocity is square of k^2 over k s+ m^ 2
the phase velocity isqu k^2 + m^2 over
k^2 they're inverse to each other this
one is greater than one this one is
always less than
one okay this one is less than one in
fact this is the velocity of a
relativistic particle with momentum
k k Square thank
you yeah they're just inverse to each
other and as it happens as was pointed
out by some somebody uh the product of
the group velocity the group velocity
and the phase velocity are equal to one
so they're just inverses of each other
now that's somewhat accidental that that
that's not a very general fact yeah
buried in there somewhere is that the
wave speed must be a function of
frequency what the wave speed must be a
function of frequency if the wave speed
is is constant of frequency you get no
dispersion that's right that's that's
this case here where Omega is equal or
proportional to uh uh to
K that's the case where all waves have
the same velocity right so it's only in
the case where all the waves of
different frequency have the same
velocity that the group and phase
velocity are the same that's a good
approximation not only for light it also
happens to be a good approximation for
sound and other things uh to at least
low frequency sound waves all move with
pretty much the same velocity and so
they um they
that's right that's right so it's that's
right that's right so the difference of
these two kinds of velocities is
connected with wave dispersion with the
with the changes with the fact that
waves change shape absolutely
absolutely okay so that's the that's the
story about waves uh about group
velocity and phase velocity and as I
said in quantum mechanics because the
effect for example here the effect of an
additive shift in Omega is no
physical effect whatever it's an example
of the fact that most times the phase
velocity is irrelevant to real physical
propagation of any signals or any energy
flow or anything like that probability
flow question a moment AG last you said
that you can't measure uh the uh fa
phase velocity when because these these
complex conjugates are those at least at
least for the shinger wave yeah okay
right can you meure for a photon well
for a photon they're the same they're
the same they're the same now it gets a
little more complicated when you have
various kinds of dispersive materials
that the photon can move through but um
you know that's for these squalet State
physicists think
about is all this waves don't spread out
all the
time yeah what what's true for w waves
that don't spread out out over time are
the ones for which all waves have the
same
velocity if different components of the
wave have different
velocities then it's going to spread out
all right all right so that's a that's
the case where Omega is a nonlinear
function of K
basically uh if Omega is a linear
function of K then uh then they don't
spread
out and that's the case of all waves
having one universal
velocity okay at some point maybe if
somebody comes back and asks me this
question about light cones and things we
can come back to it but uh it was a good
question but it it's not quite related
to
this all right let's see was there
anything else I wanted
to fill in before getting to
firion yeah uh before getting to
firmians let's discuss the issue of
momentum conservation we discussed the
issue of energy conservation and I
showed you an example it was really just
an example of uh how the time
translation in
variance of the amplitudes that go into
a scattering process in in Quantum field
Theory uh conserve energy I'll just
remind you very quickly and then show
you how the energy the momentum
conservation works very very similar
we will come back to these
things but then I want to get on to
Fons that's what I want
to get to tonight okay let's uh let's
get back where were we I was going to
talk about momentum conservation just
really quickly do you remember how
energy conservation worked energy
conservation we had for example some
process it doesn't matter what it is a
bunch of Sai creation operators no a
bunch of s Annihilation operators a
bunch of s creation
operators act on a state with a bunch of
particles in it with
momenta and then we calculate the
overlap or the inner product or the
probability amplitude for a final state
with a bunch of other particles K Prime
blah blah blah blah blah okay these
fields act on the initial state
these fields act on the final States and
I'll just uh remind remind you a little
bit how it worked we said supposing all
the processes take place at the same
point of space and time at the same
point or the example that I gave was one
in which one particle came in one
particle went out and they came in and
Scattered off a point in space but we
integrated over all possible time
the particle was there not this particle
but the the uh the target was there at
all times and so the particle could have
scattered at any time whenever it gets
there and that's represented by
integrating this over
time if you remember each one of these
size or each one of these size is made
up out of a bunch of things
involving A's e to the i kx's and e to
the minus I Omega
T's omegas being the energies K's being
the momenta now if we said all of this
took place at the origin of spatial
coordinates space
coordinates then this is just equal to
one and when the operators act and we're
finished calculating everything
the only time dependence in this
amplitude comes from these e to the I
Omega TS let me remind you what it
looked like it looked like e to Theus I
Omega of each
momentum K1 t e to the minus I Omega of
K2 T dot dot dot dot that's for the
initial States and then for the final
states there was something similar e to
the + I
Omega K Prime 1 blah blah blah blah blah
time
T blah blah blah means the sum of all of
the outgoing momentum and here it's
minus the sum of all the incoming
momenta Omega K incoming times
T the last step was to say if we
integrate this over all times
representing the fact that the
scattering can happen at any times the
integral of this gives what integral
over
time a Delta function a Delta function
of the sum of the final momentum minus
the initial
momentum sorry final energies minus the
initial energies when we integrate this
over time
what we get is a direct Delta function
of let's call it Omega final that means
the sum of all the incoming energy
outgoing energies minus the sum of all
the incoming
energies in other words the answer is
zero unless the incoming energies are
equal to the outgoing energies and this
was just as a consequence of saying that
the process could happen with equal
probability at any time
okay now what about momentum
conservation momentum conservation is
exactly the same sort of thing except it
has to do with space
translation if a process can happen at
any point of space with equal
probability then it's momentum that's
conserved let me give you just one
example one very simple example this is
a
process in which a
particle comes in and splits
into two
particles okay can this really happen in
nature yes it can really happen in
nature particles
Decay okay particles
Decay and an incoming particle of one
momentum can Decay into particles of
other momenta but as you know momentum
is conserved but let's see if we can see
why that is so the incoming particle is
described well of course it's described
by particle coming in the outgoing
particles this is K outgoing particles
are K Prime 1 and K Prime
2 the operator which eats the initial
particle let's call that
s
of X this represents the particle being
absorbed at point x and then two
particles created also at point
x that's a simple example two part one
particle is eaten at point x and then it
spits out two
particles uh also at the same point for
Simplicity all right but it could happen
at any place it could happen at any
place and that means we have to
integrate this over all space let's see
what we get
again these
size have creation and Annihilation
operators there's some Annihilation
operator in here which can annihilate or
just work on this particle eat that
particle that's some a minus of K and it
has an e to the I KX in it let's forget
the uh the omegas we don't need the the
time dependence in here all right so
that's the operator which eats this
particle over here and then there's
these two part operators which put back
the particles over here and they give us
some A+ of K1 Prime A+ of K2
Prime and then there's an e to the minus
I K1 plus K2
Prime X same
X these operators act they annihilate
the particles we calculate the Matrix
element that's all trivial the only
thing of Interest that's left over is
this function of position this is the
amplitude that the process happened at
point x but then since X is not a
special place it could happen anywhere
we integrate
it over x what do we get when we
integrate it over x a Delta function of
momentum
conservation right so if a process can
happen with translation and variance in
space
then it will conserve momentum and in
fact it didn't matter how many particles
were coming in and going out in this
little demonstration here would work the
same way translation
invariance or the idea that the process
Could Happen anywhere as with equal
amplitude that's momentum conservation
the idea that it can happen with equal
probability at any time that's energy
conservation there was another symmetry
we talked about a little
bit the other symmetry that we talked
about a little bit was a possible
symmetry if we multiply
s by e to the I times let's call it
Lambda in other words just change the
phase of
s what will that do to
probability
amplitudes well the answer is it will do
nothing to them as long as there's the
same number of size inside
daggers if there's the same number of
sze inside daggers that's the same thing
as saying that the number of particles
coming in is the same as the number of
particles going
out and
so symmetry with respect to changing the
phase of the wave function like that
just multiplying it by an overall phase
and multiplying its complex conjugate by
the opposite phase that's associated
with certain conservation laws such as
conservation of electric charge
conservation of electric charge tells us
that
uh is
um
contained in symmetries of this type
here if these were charge carrying
Fields charge carrying Fields mean
fields for electrons for example if they
were fields for
electrons then this symmetry would be
correct only if there were as many
electrons in the initial State as in the
final State this is of course a law of
nature that charge is
conserved so the law of nature the
charge is conserved is the same as the
Symmetry under changing the phase of the
wave function these are some examples of
symmetries all right though that was
quick review now I want to move on to
the notion of A
Thon yeah when you're doing the
integration over space that's overall
three spatial
yeah say that would mean conservation of
all three components of the momentum
exactly yeah then if you have two
positive KS and a negative K the K may
have a
distribution in other words you could
have one is larger one is smaller the
other one is yes yes yes is there
anything here that can point
to some relative probability for
different ways that the momentum is
shared yeah not that not for not for not
for this case here for this case here
it's basically neutral with respect to
the ways the momentum is shared can't
say anything here just uh nothing we'll
come back to these things um the kinds
of we'll come back to it we'll come back
to it I simply wanted to uh uh to give
some very very simple illustrations of
the connection between symmetries and
conservation laws and how Quantum fields
are used to describe
physical processes of creation and
annihilation of of particles yeah a
technical question I I have in my notes
where we have the uh a we were doing a
sum overc of annihilation operator times
e to the plus IX times some State and I
wrote that it reduces to one
term which the state has a particle in
it that's right there's one only one
particle there's one particle and I'm
annihilating right by summing over K and
I I wrote that it reduces to one term
right and I I wanted to ask whether that
means that if I if the terms which are
annihilating places where there are no
particles they just don't giv you zero
Vector gives you zero yeah zero Vector
right zero vector or zero it's nothing
at all all right let's just let's
now uh
um depart from the theory of
bons the characteristic of
bons is first of all you can have any
number of them in any Quantum
State and as we described a couple of
lectures ago they have a
tendency uh to want to accumulate in the
same state an example of that is if a
particle decays and produces a photon
for example and an atom decays and
produces a photon it may produce a
photon in any direction with any
momentum uh with some un some
probability distribution but if at the
same time as it the case there happens
to be a large number of photons all in
the same state in other words all moving
the same way with the same energy and
the same frequency it will
preferentially Decay so that the photon
comes out has the same momentum as the
extra photons which are already there
that's these square roots of
n uh that occur in the ban
operators fans are very different Fons
don't like each other they don't like to
congregate into the same state in fact
they simply can't be in the same
state this of course was a discovery
that was first made by po I guess was it
po yeah sure po Exclusion
Principle uh in the context of
atoms that two electrons never occupy
the same Quantum state within an
atom and that was generalized by poy
himself po fmy others uh to a powerful
principle that Fons are particles that
simply can never be in the same Quantum
state in atoms out of atoms
anywhere uh very different than
bans okay let's uh work out some of the
mathematics or some of the bookkeeping
the mathematics of creation Annihilation
operators is really a form of
bookkeeping useful
bookkeeping um but let's try to work out
a theory of quantum fields of Fons
particles that can never be in the same
state well we start
with the same kind of construction as we
did for bans imagine a Quantum
field s of
X which is again exactly the same
formula as for bans summation over all
of the allowed
momenta I guess I call it K usually all
of the allowed K if the allowed K or
continuous it becomes an
integral Annihilation operator for
particle of momentum
k e to the I
KX the states of the system are again
labeled by how many particles there are
in each Quantum state but the rule is
never more than one so the state of the
system is a bunch of zeros and
ones never more than one particle in the
same
state that's the the character of a
firmon now are there other kinds of
things that can have three particles in
the same state but not more or that must
have more than seven particles in the
same state or other odd
varieties the answer is
no uh but to prove that the mathematics
of quantum mechanics together with
special relativity dictate that the only
possibilities of fans and bosons would
take us far beyond this CL CL so we're
not going to do that but we are going to
describe what a firon is all right so
this is exactly the same this formula is
exactly the same as for bans sagora of X
same thing incidentally this is all non
relativistic particles we've not got to
relativistic particles eventually we
will but what do the creation same thing
with uh creation
operators a plus of K
e to the I KX but now the rule is a
little different than
before yeah there is a minus sign all
right so now let's focus just on one
possible
momentum of the electron or this could
be an electron now let's focus on one
partic on one possible State not worry
about all of the states but let's just
say some particular Quantum State it's
either filled with an electron or it's
empty those are the only two
possibilities let's represent that I
guess we can represent that by
zero that represents no electron in that
state or one that represents one
electron in that state this isn't
multiplying this this is just two
possible States put a comma
here what is the algebra or the um the
abstract mathematics of the creation and
annihilation
operators let's see what we let's see if
we can make some
guesses you'll make the
guess a creation
operator on the state with no
particle you want to
guess one particle
what else could it
be what about a creation operator on the
state with one
particle zero now zero does not mean the
state with no particles it just means
there's zero
Vector I don't write that as with a just
zero doesn't mean anything or they're
just uh is not a vector at all it's a
it's a nonstate
H what's
that
louder yeah they're all linear operators
in quantum mechanics all operators are
linear
operators all when one speaks about an
operator especially in quantum mechanics
it's always a linear operator I think
mathematical terminology is that
operator usually means maybe always
means linear operator and otherwise it's
operation but I'm not sure uh but yes in
quantum mechanics operators are always
linear
operators okay let's see if we can make
some more guesses what about a minus on
o well you can't take away that which is
not
there but what about a minus on the
state with one
particle no
particles no no particles
all right so these are operators
which well they do what they do they do
what they do just clarify the zero there
that means that doesn't happen you can't
do that yeah
yeah um Let me Give an example if we
described harmonic oscillators by wave
functions ordinary wave functions then
there would be a wave function for the
ground state and the wave function for
the ground state let let's just discuss
this for a minute the wave function for
the ground state would be some gaussian
wave function like e to Theus x^2 all
right that would be the wave function
this would be identified as the ground
state and therefore the state with no
excitations on the other hand the wave
function s of X which is literally equal
to
zero that's the state zero no wave
function at all right probability is
just zero doesn't uh it's it's not a
state it's just a
nothing okay that's the this is the
starting point for the algebra of
fironic creation and Annihilation
operators there's nothing in the
notation that helps us distinguish
between the fans and the bosons thing
well uh yes I suppose we should yeah
it's a good point we should probably use
a different
letter uh
uh let's not call fironic operators
a we could call them Alpha sometimes
they you sometimes C is used why don't I
use
C
okay well the problem is that there are
many incon many different not
inconsistent but many different
notations in the literature and I guess
for us we probably are wise to to use a
notation
where bosonic and fermionic operators
have different letters associated with
them so let's call a
c this is a common notation also that uh
that fironic operators are labeled
C but they are the analog for fans of
the A's for bosan
okay
whoops all right let's see if we can
figure out what C dagger C or C+ * C
minus does what does that operator do
when it acts on anything all right so
let's figure out what it does what
happens when it acts on
o well C minus when it acts on o just
gives
zero and C+ isn't going to do is not
going to be helpful in getting it back
to being non zero Z is zero so this is
zero you simply can't take away what's
not there okay even if you try to put it
back afterwards you can't take it away
to begin
with what about
C minus * C+ on
o what does that
give C+ when it gives o gives
what one one and then C
minus
o let's call it o let's call this o as
opposed to zero so this gives back the
state in other words it gives back
exactly the same
state it gives back exactly the same
state
uh what about C+ C minus plus C minus
C+ if it acts on
O Let's
see what does it give when it acts on
o we're just adding those two equations
right we're just gives
O Okay the ground state right
sometimes known as the vacuum all right
let's now do the same thing acting on
one what is C minus C+ acting on
one well C minus when it acts on one
takes the particle away and leaves o the
vacuum and then C+ puts it back
right so this gives one back
again what does it give when it acts on
one
one acting on
one that's minus yeah that's correct
isn't it yeah okay now what happens when
we do
this Z it's zero because we can't add
another particle to one that's already
present if it's a firon so this is
zero what happens if we add these state
if we add these two equations we find
again C+ C
minus plus C minus
C+ on
one gives
one so
two equal to
I yeah both of these operators well this
operator this particular combination
when it acts on any state gives back
exactly the same state
right so that's written in Opera
notation by saying C+ C minus plus C
minus
C+ is equal to the unit operator it
just gives back the same state whatever
it acts
on this
combination an operator times another
plus The Interchange what what would you
call it if there was a minus here you
would call it the commut Ator all right
with a plus here it's called the
anticommutator that's what it's called
and it's the symbol for it is a curly
bracket sometimes use
a
sometimes curly
bracket curly bracket of A and
B is by definition AB plus ba a
okay so the first thing we learn is the
creation and Annihilation operators
anticommute to give one on the right
hand side this is incidentally the
analog oh in yeah it doesn't matter
which order you write them in uh since
they're the same well no sorry they're
not the same but doesn't matter which
order you write them in c plus c minus C
minus C plus same
thing this is the analog for bons of the
commut of a minus with
A+ is equal to 1 it's the analog it's
not the same thing but it's the analog
in this case it's
commutator for bons in this case it's
anticommutator now what about the
anticommutator of C+ with
C+ the anti-c commutator of C+ with c C+
is just C+ C+ plus C+
C+ it's just twice C+
s twice
this what does this give when it acts on
anything well if it acts on the vacuum
it can create a particle but then the
next one is going to try to create a
particle on top of a particle which is
already there you can't do that if it
acts on a particle which is already
there can't do that
so whatever it acts on C+ C+ always
gives zero all right so C+ C+ gives
zero what about C minus C minus Ain't
That commutator C minus C
minus that's just twice C minus
squar if it acts on a state with a
particle the first operator removes a
particle and the second one looks for a
particle can't find one and says zero
if it acts on a state without a particle
it also gives
zero this is the analog for harmonic
oscillators of
commutators is that zero or
o
z no on cus C Min is that the vector no
this is an operator it's not a vector
right operator zero yeah it's the
operator
zero right it's the operator zero the
operator zero is such that when it acts
on any vector or any state it gives
zero it really is literally zero
whenever it acts it just doesn't give
anything it gives
zero there's an operator which is zero
and there's a vector which is zero not a
vector but a state Vector a state Vector
which is zero two different uses of zero
but they're both zero
and in fact when the zero operator acts
on any Vector State Vector it gives the
state equal to zero zero
Vector okay so Fons and
bosons are have a parallel mathematics
to each other where wherever you see
commutator for bosons you replace it by
anticommutator for Fons and it is a
consequence of this that you can't put
to Parc in the same state if you try
that's trying to put C+ C+ on
o and C+ * C+ is zero okay that's what
this state that's what this equation
says C+ C+ plus C+ C+ is equal to
zero so this
algebra incorporates and encompasses the
idea that you cannot put two particles
into the same state described by these
creation and Annihilation
operators I want to prove a little
observation about
this these C's here create and
annihilate particles with given
momentum right what we prove what we've
assumed it's some combination of prove
and assume prove from the from the Zan
oh oh incidentally yeah we should write
this more completely supposing we're now
talking about creation Annihilation
operators for different momenta K and K
Prime then I will just tell you this is
Delta k k
Prime in other words it's one if k
equals K Prime zero otherwise and these
and these things are always just
zero C minus C minus
are just equal to
zero for all K and K
Prime that's the algebra of creation and
Annihilation operators which if you like
by definition this defines the algebra
of creation and Annihilation operators
for
firion the fact that it really does
describe Fons in nature of course is a
marvelous uh uh uh correspondence
between mathematics simple mathematics
and some
Physics but here's an interesting
question as defined up till now what
this says is that you cannot put two
particles into the same momentum State
you cannot make two particles carrying
the same momentum two
Fons two Fons of the same kind
incidentally two Fons of the same
species you cannot put them in into the
same state momentum
State can you put them into the same
position State we what this tells us is
that if we find a particle with momentum
K firon an electron we cannot find
another one with exactly the same
Quantum State same momentum what about
the same position can we find two
particles uh at the same place in not in
momentum but in position so let's try to
find
out how do we create a particle at point
x we create a particle at point x using
S of x s of
X on the vacuum represents a particle at
point
x h oh sorry uh I think we should have
sidea huh
yeah creation operators so the question
is what happens if you try to create two
at the same
point well let's see what we have that
means we're going to have a sum over a k
and a k
Prime
of C+ of
K C+ of K Prime
and
then let's do it uh let's do it at the
origin let's just do it at position
zero then these Z to the ixs aren't
there on
zero
well what is this anybody tell what this
is
you're all terms are zero when K does
not equal K
Prime no no there zero there zero in any
case you can rewrite this in the form C+
of K C+ of K Prime 12 C+ of K plus 12 C+
of K
Prime C+ of
K because it's under the summation here
but this is just the anti-commutation
anticommutator of C+ are all equal to
zero so this is
zero why why because the anti-
commutator of C+ is
zero why
zero you should have asked me that
before because I wrote it on the
Blackboard well yeah yeah no right right
all of this is very clear if we're
talking about only
1K right it gets some real impact
nontrivial impact when we generalize it
in this fashion here to all K and K
Prime all right so there there's a
basically some Physics that's going in
here and what is that physics it's the
physics that not only can't you put two
particles into the same momentum state
but you can't put them into the same
position state for example what I'm
showing you is that with this
algebra if this algebra is correct then
it's not just that you can't put two
particles into the same momentum State
you can't put them into the same
position state in fact you can't put
them into the same state all together uh
but this was just an example with this
algebra it says that you cannot put
particles either into the same momentum
State or the same position state or any
other state for that matter so these are
firion this is the pattern for firion
Yeah question I've always maybe
misunderstood that that you could have
two electrons in the same momentum if
they were far far yeah yeah uh the
correct statement is you can't have two
electrons in the same state now what
constitutes a state the constitutes a
state may not just be its momentum it
may be its momentum and its
spin okay uh which we haven't come to
yet this is one of the things we're
going to come to shortly is the concept
of spin very important concept we
haven't come to it yet so at this stage
we're imagining that a particle is
characterized by a momentum and if it's
a firon you can't have two in the same
momentum now the correct statement is of
course you can't have them in the same
state and if a state requires other
ingredients besides its momentum for
example it's spin then you can't have
two particles with the same momentum
with the same spin but spin there's only
really parallel and anti- parallel but
what about electrons and two hydrogen
atoms that are separated some distance
away each other would they have could
they possibly have the same momentum
momentum or M momentum I'm just want to
stay with momentum you want the atoms or
the the hyd just well just an electron I
maybe use the bad example well electrons
in a hydrogen atom are not in momentum
States they're
in atomic energy levels okay now the
atomic energy levels over here and over
here for two different different atoms
are two quite different wave functions
so if you had an atom over
here an electron might occupy a wave
function that looks something like this
another atom over here might have an
electron which looks like this this wave
function and that wave function are not
the same right they're quite
distinguishable by the fact that one of
them's over here one of them's over here
so yes you can have two electrons in two
different atoms both for example in the
ground state in in some particular state
yes but you can't have two electrons in
the same atom with the same quantum
numbers be more
generic just to be more generic instead
of specific talking about atoms or could
you just use the term systems is that
used in in states is the right statement
the the right the right nomenclature is
you can't have two electrons in the same
Quantum State okay in the same Quantum
State yeah a system
means a collection of degrees of freedom
but it doesn't imply a particular
state so an electron is a system an
electron can be in a particular State
all right so the nomenclature is
electron is a system the state of the
electron is perhaps some particular
orbital State uh orbital and spin state
in the in a particular
atom can I just carry that one further
let's suppose you have an electron beam
in a picture to Cath right to yeah you
have a stream of electrons so that means
that no two of those in that little
glass jar will yeah they really look
like this so packet over here and
another packet over here and another
packet over here and another packet over
here and they're not in the same
state
the that's they're not they're not in
the same momentum they're not in the
same position right in in big contrast
to the idea of
photons photons March down the axis all
for example in the same
plain wave right that's why you can't
build up a coherent beam of electrons in
the same sense that you can have a
coherent beam of uh you just can't put
more than one of them in the same state
so a a firmon is in many respects a
bigger abstraction than a bone can you
have two electrons in the same place
with different momenta no no no no no no
no no no no you remember you either
describe a thing by a position or a
momentum and not both position and
momentum are intertwined mutually
incompatible right so it's it's only
like Spin and position that yeah that's
because spin commutes with momentum and
position all right but position and
momentum don't commute so you can't
speak about an electron at a position
with a momentum but you can speak about
an electron at a position with a with a
particular spin is there some sense in
which this bound electron over here and
that bound electron are therefore in
that sense in a position representation
or
something
well uh they're not at position igen
states because the wave function isn't
that concentrated but they approximately
are they're approximately located at the
position of the
atom you can't put two of them into the
same atom in the same way but you can
have two different atoms which is like
having an electron over here and an
electron over here that's
fine yes so what is the definition of a
state yeah what is the definition of a
state I think I would have to refer you
either to my own lectures or a book on
quantum mechanics but it just means it's
the quantum
mechanical analog of the config
configuration of a
system the configuration of a system a
system is a collection of degrees of
freedom there a collection of
coordinates and momenta and things like
that a state is a particular value in
classical mechanics of the positions and
momenta in quantum mechanics the state
of an electron is the everything you
have to specify about the electron to
State all the things it can be measured
about the
electron it's a wave function
actually yeah can you're electron here
an electron let's say driving a g elron
can they be in the same state no
obviously not one of them's here and one
of them's in and dromic Galaxy that's
pretty
different it's like saying can suppose
you have one in Nevada and one in
Connecticut can they be in the same
state they have the same state of
momentum what's that they can have the
same momentum I mean they can both be
going east well if you know where they
are it means you don't really know their
momentum with infinite Precision so if
you know anything about where they are
it means that you don't completely know
the momentum but yes to within the
extent that an electron in Nevada can
have a pretty well-defined
momentum but still not so well
defined that it might be in Connecticut
right well defined but not so well
defined that it might be in
Connecticut then yes you can have an
electron in the VOD an electron in
Connecticut which have pretty much the
the same
momentum but if you really Tred to make
that momentum infinitely sharp that
electron in NADA would be equally likely
to be in Connecticut the one in
Connecticut would be equally likely to
be in Nevada and you simply can't put
them both into the same state you just
multiply the uncertainty by together and
you get planks constantly
greater okay so we now know what a fa on
is more or less
we use the algebra of these operators in
a very similar
way we write down Expressions involving
electron operators which annihilate
electrons or which take electrons out of
the initial
State creation operators which put
electrons into the final State we can
even multiply them by by um by operators
for photons photons incidentally being
bosons and we can
write mathematical expressions for the
uh process of some number of electrons
coming in some number of electrons going
out plus a bunch of photons and we can
write similar kinds of
um
bookkeeping as we used to
describe just the simple processes
involving bosons and we're not going to
go into that now I mean it's uh it's it
is the story of particle physics how you
describe the those
reactions but before we get to
that I want to talk a little more about
the differences between Fons and
bons question yeah on the two State
example M um is the poly exclusion
principle of uh locally
communicated is it globally enforced
instantly like
entanglement
um words if you had if you had two
different processes going on in Nevada
Connecticut they're both about to create
particle but if they're in if they're in
if one is known to be in Nevada and the
other is known to be in Connecticut then
they're not in the same state period
yeah but let's say it's not known let's
just say there's a there's a slight
probability difference so there's a
certain amount of
fuzziness here's the
situation let's imagine that Nevada is a
point and Connecticut is a point instead
of a big state here's a point here's
Nevada and here's
Connecticut an electron located right at
the center of Nevada I'll call
n n for Nevada not for n for Neutron not
n for anything else not let's call it
capital N
incidentally n is not an integer it's
just Nevada all right an electron in
Connecticut I will call C
now there's a Quantum state of an
electron which is a superposition of
being in Nevada and Connecticut it has
some probability of being in Nevada and
some probability of being Connecticut
Nevada plus Connecticut this is one
electron with equal probability you
should put a one over Square < TK of two
here to make the probability come out to
be
one this is a state of an electron which
has equal probab ility of being in
Nevada or Connecticut it's a Quantum
State and if you look for that electron
you'll either find it at the center of
Nevada or the center of Connecticut with
an equal
probability okay incidentally there is
another state like this which is
orthogonal to it which has a minus sign
here okay what you can't have is two
electrons both in this Quantum state
you can have one electron in Nevada one
electron in Connecticut but you can't
have two electrons which are in this
state of both being equally shared
between Nevada and Connecticut now that
has implications that probably not at
all obvious to you what those
implications
are but supposing we try to make two
electrons in this state you can't do it
you can't have two electrons which are
equally shared in this way between the
body and kinetic can can one have a plus
sign the
other yes one can have a plus sign and
the other have a minus sign yes yes yes
yes yes one electron can be in the state
with a plus sign the other one in the
state with a minus sign and we're
talking about at the same time here H
we're talking about at the same time
absolutely we're talking about the same
time so so the ambiguity then is nada
and Connecticut are spatially separated
M and so there's there's a question what
do you mean by have the same
simultaneity um but when you think about
in the momentum space you don't have the
spatial
separation remember we're doing
non-relativistic physics so there's no
limitations of the speed of light in
making experiments and so
forth at the same time I mean the same
time somebody can jump from here to
there in no time at all in check what
happens when you're throwing
relativistic physics Sy not much
not
much not
much
um there is an additional fuzziness
because of Relativity about how
particles are located but for the moment
I wanted to deal with the
non-relativistic
ideas let's uh let's
come to the ground state of a system of
bons and the ground state of a system of
an elect of electrons to see how
different uh they
are let's imagine the three-dimensional
world and since I can never draw three
dimensions I will only draw
two but I'm and
um I want to plot all of the possible
allowable
momenta two-dimensional momentum
this is the X component of momentum this
is the Y component I really want three
dimensions but as I said I can't draw
it uh
of electrons electrons confined to be in
a certain finite volume the finite
volume is very much like when we studied
one dimension we studied electrons on an
interval of length
L with periodic boundary conditions but
that's not so important here
uh if electrons are confined or
particles are confined to be within a
given
volume then the momenta are
discrete remember when the electron was
moving on the Periodic interval it had
momenta uh which had to be what was it
uh n
uh n / L and there's a 2 pi in there 2
pi n /
L is equal to
K right so what did we say we said if we
drew the momentum axis the possible
values of momentum were
discrete and that was a consequence of
the space being finite space available
to the particle being
finite the bigger L is the closer these
levels get all right let's continue to
think about things confined in a finite
volume in that case both the X and Y
ands Z components of the momentum would
again be discrete so the allowable
values of the momentum Vector
would form a
lattice this is not space this is
momentum space the values of the
possible momentum
vectors let's put zero right over here
at the center
and then they go on and on forever not
the it's not bounded just goes on and on
forever just like this axis goes on and
on forever this n can be
anything so these are the possible
allowable values of the momentum of a
particle in a periodic three-dimensional
box okay let's start with
bans let's take a collection of in bons
all identical to each other they're all
the same kind of particle and let's put
them into our box and let's look for the
ground state the state of lowest energy
well let's put the first bon in what the
where will it go if it's supposed to go
into the state of lowest
Energy Zero Zero what zero
momentum zero momentum in other words
we'll put the B on in that's zero this
is KX KY KZ is equal to zero right at
that point that's the single particle
state of lowest energy remember the
energy is k^2 over 2
m the lowest possible energy for that
Bon is to carry zero
momentum if we want to find the ground
state we just put in the particle with
zero momentum now supposing we want to
add another particle to
it another Bon of the same mind where do
we put it to keep uh the the energy as
low as
possible same
place H right just the same place we put
two particles in at the same place in
fact we put all in particles in at the
same
place that'll be the state of lowest
energy okay so that is called a BAC
condensate it's roughly the idea of a
boa condensate is a long large number of
particles all in the same state but in
this case all in the lowest energy State
available incidentally the lowest energy
State available since it has the lowest
momentum fills up it's a wave function
which fills up the
box it's a wave function which fills up
the box and so the wave function of each
one of these particles fills up the
box and we simply put a lot of particles
in all of them very uncertain about
where they are in the Box put a lot of
them in that's first of all called the
boa condensate and it's also the ground
state of a system of
bans the uh large number of particles
builds up a kind of classical field
strength so that the Schrodinger wave
function is pretty
classical okay that's very very
different than what would happen if we
had
inmons let's forget spin they're not
going to be interested in spin now where
if we where should we put the first one
we're going to put them one at a time we
want to keep the energy as low as
possible okay obviously the first one to
go in we want to put in to the lowest
State what about the next
one whatever the next energy level is
over here the next one would maybe go
over here there happen to be four states
of the same energy so we could put it
here here here or here this is in two
dimensions in three dimensions there
would be what um uh six Six States
altogether so by the time we put in five
electrons they will fill up these states
here now let's put in some more
electrons we can't put them in the same
state forbidden so the next one will go
in in the next lowest energy level which
will be over here incidentally the
energy being proportional to K squ is
proportional to the distance squared
from the origin
so what we want to do to keep the energy
as low as low as possible is crowd the
electrons in in momentum space into as
small
a
sphere as we can in other words when we
have a lot of electrons and we put them
in they will fill up in momentum
space they'll fill up a sphere
there might be a little confusion about
uh about the jaggedness of the uh
spherical edge here but that's not
important this of course will have a lot
more energy than the corresponding boson
system the corresponding boson system
had all of its particles in the lowest
energy if you look for a particle all
you will find is a particle of zero
momentum in the ground state of the
minion system you will find the more
firion you put in the higher the maximum
momentum will be there will be lots and
lots and lots of particles of large
momentum and of course only a handful at
low momentum because there aren't that
many states at low momentum there are
clearly more States within a given Shell
at large momentum so first of all the
energy of the system will be much
higher
putting Fons into a
um uh into a
box costs more energy one number two
there's this pattern that they fill up a
sphere out to some boundary where the
boundary is determined by how many
electrons you
have depending on the number of
electrons it will fill a sphere and that
sphere is called the fmis spere it's
called a fmis spere
and like the history of this is a little
bit confused it was Dau figured out Fons
and that's why they're called
Fons Einstein will figured out bans and
that's why they called
bans no they all contributed very
heavily to the
subject anyway this is the ground state
of a collection of Fons fills the feris
spere let's draw over here the
corresponding thing in momentum space
this is all in momentum space I don't
need to draw these lines uh just all the
particles condensed at the center of the
momentum space for bosons bosons
firion let's put a little bit of this
lattice in so we can see where the next
states are okay what's the first what's
the first excited state we have in
bans they're all at the center what's
the first energy level above the ground
state well that's easy we take one ban
and move it to the next energy level we
take out one bon in the ground state and
put it into the first excited state
which one which Bon do we do doesn't
matter they're all the same so we have n
minus one bans in the ground state and
one bon in the first excited state the
uh there are four first excited States
that's not so
important um the second excited state it
might correspond depending on the
details it might correspond to putting
one electron in the second excited state
or two electrons in the first excited
state but one one excited not electrons
bons a variety of different things but
you can see the way the pattern to
excite the system to give it more energy
is to take electrons from the ground
state and put them into higher energy
states
okay let's come to the firion system
well it's also very
similar but let's try to figure out
exactly what would correspond to the
lowest Yeah
question okay what would correspond
maybe not to the exact lowest energy
state but to the very very low energy
states above the ground state we want to
give it just a little bit of energy
what's the cheapest way to give it
energy should we take an electron from
the center here and move it outside we
can't move an electron to someplace
inside the fmis spere because there's
already an electron there right I think
as you were about to say it wouldn't be
too smart to take one deep inside the
FIS spere and bring it to the outside
because that would take a lot of energy
it takes how much energy you're going to
take one out of low energy and put it
back at relatively high energy that's
pretty costly what's the cheapest thing
right take one from very near the
surface of the sphere inside the sphere
and move it to the outside how much
energy does that cost not much because
you've taken a pretty high energy
electron and just displaced it a little
bit in
energy right so that creates an electron
out here with a little bit of energy
above the edge of the firis spere but it
also leaves something it leaves a hole
in the fere sphere behind
it that
hole is a thing let's suppose these are
really electrons okay let's let's uh
let's consider a real world
situation we have a box and that box is
full of a positive charge the positive
charge is protons of course or or nuclei
but for Simplicity let's just imagine
the positive charge is smeared over the
box and then we put electrons in on top
of it
and we put enough electrons in to fill
up a fmis spere like this right it's
electrically neutral because there are
as many electrons as there are protons
in the box so it's electrically
neutral in the ground state the firion
fill up this fmy surface this fmis spere
here now we take an electron out from
just below the fmis spere and put it in
just above the fmis spere we have not
changed the charge it's still
electrically neutral but we have created
one extra particle with a little bit of
extra energy above the fmy surface and
left a hole in the fmy
surface oh left a hole with a missing
particle a missing
particle just think of it literally as a
whole it's an absence of a bit of
negative charge a bit of negative charge
with a certain momentum over here it can
be thought of as the presence of a
positive
charge
hole right a hole can be thought of as a
kind of particle in this context a hole
behaves as a
particle is it a particle with negative
energy because it's below the
firy no let's let's see how much energy
it takes how much energy does it take to
move a particle from here to
here well
got a square and
it's energy well let's just say we took
out a particle of energy let's call the
particle that we took out let's call it
energy Epsilon and we put in another
particle of energy Epsilon
Prime when we took out the particle of
momentum of energy all right how much
energy does that cost
difference the difference
some of the
difference I think the difference you
think the difference I think the
some
okay
well
no I'm sorry I'm sorry let me be let me
be more precise let
me it is the difference but uh
we I'm I'm getting tired I'm reaching a
point
of the point is it cost some energy it
costs some energy I'll tell you how much
energy later but you have to push energy
into the system in order to pop an
electron up to the next energy level
yeah so you're adding energy well the
point is you how much energy do you have
to put in you have to put in the the
amount of energy that it would take to
remove this particle and bring it
exactly to the firmy surface and then an
additional amount of energy to bring it
from the firmy surface off the firmy
surface all right so here's the
picture
um here's the firm sphere the FY surface
is the edge of the fmy sphere all right
let's take a particle just below the fmy
surface bring it from here to here how
much energy does it take well it takes
two bits of positive energy we can count
it this way the first bit of positive
energy is the energy that it would take
to remove this particle and bring it
right to the firmy
surface that's a little bit of positive
energy to bring it to here and then a
little more positive energy to bring it
to
here so it's actually the sum of two
positive terms the two positive terms
being the absolute value of the
difference of the energies from the
firmy surface you have to add two little
bits of energy one of them can be
thought of as the energy of the electron
over here measured relative the fmy
surface and the other one can be thought
of as the energy of the hole and they're
both positive okay this one has a bit of
positive charge because it's an electron
this one has a bit of negative charge
because it's a missing no
sorry this one has a bit of negative
charge because it's a positron no
I did that on
purpose I didn't this one was a bit of
negative charge because it's an electron
and this one has a bit of positive
charge because it's a hole thank
you right now this electron could be
moving
around and then suddenly pop into that
hole the hole is available now the hole
is available for the electron to drop
down into just as an electron can drop
from an excited level of an atom down to
an
unoccupied Quantum state if there's an
unoccupied Quantum State this electron
can drop down into this hole what will
happen when an electron drops its energy
and uh drops down into the
hole well energy has to be conserved so
the energy of the electron has
decreased a photon is emitted all right
you can say it another way you can say
an electron comes together with a hole
and annihilates the electron annihilates
the whole and a photon or a photon or
more than one Photon some number of
photons goes out so you can speak about
this in the language that a hole is a
kind of particle of course it's a fake
particle it's not a real particle in the
real sense of the word but it's a kind
of fake particle that has the opposite
charge of the true
R it can be counted as having some
positive energy and when the electron
drops down into the hole you can think
of it as the electron and hole coming
together annihilating and producing some
heat radiation whatever the process of
annihilation question yeah when you say
you're moving is El you're moving from
one lattice point to another lattice
Point you're not lce in momentum space
yeah no no no you're moving them from
one energy level to
another so it's the analog of having an
atom all right let's let's speak about
the analog of what this means in atomic
physics in atomic physics the Box could
be not the momentum space box but the
box that confines the electron could
just be the atom
the uh the proton at the center is some
positive charge and we fill it up with
some negative charg uh electrons of
course in this case the proton charge is
not smeared over the
atom so it's concentrated at the center
it's a little bit different but we take
an atom which has the same number of
electrons as protons and we start with
all of the electrons in the lowest
available
States lowest available States that's
the ground state of the atom uh that's
the analog of filling up the fmis spere
here now a photon comes along and hits
an electron and kicks it up into an
excited
state right Photon comes along hits an
electron just below the fmy surface and
kicks it up just above the fmy surface
it's a low energy electron a low energy
Photon so it doesn't have much energy it
can take an electron from the center
here and bring it to the outside that
would take a lot of energy it's a very
low energy Photon and so it comes in and
all it can do is hit an electron or be
absorbed by an electron near the firy
surface and kick it just above the firy
surface another language is the photon
has annihilated and been replaced by a
particle or an electron and a hole so
it's particle whole
creation by taking the energy from a
photon in the same way that a photon
hitting an atom excites the atom of
course when it excites the atom it
leaves a vacancy the vacancy in this
language is called a
Hole uh holes have yeah um so across the
whole sphere if a photon hits anything
in that sphere will it kick off
something near the edge well if it's a
low energy
Photon let's say you know some a radio
wave Photon very low
energy and it tries to get absorbed by
an electron near the center it just
can't give that electron enough energy
to get out of the
phosphere it can't jump to any place
inside the phosphere because it's
already occupied so the answer is a low
energy Photon can't be absorbed by an
electron in the interior so the
cross-section doesn't get bigger as the
sphere gets bigger it's related to the
surface not the volume yeah it all comes
off the surface that's right for a high
energy Photon of course that can kick an
electron from deep inside this is called
the language is that things inside the
fhere are in the FY sea sea this is deep
in the fmy sea this is near the surface
of the
firc only a high energy Photon or a
collection of high energy photons coming
together can kick an electron from deep
inside the
firy to the
outside a low energy Photon can take a
shallow electron or one just beneath the
surface and uh put it just above
yeah of yeah um is there anything that
keeps electrons from interacting with
electrons directly without using
phons nothing except we're ignoring
it no um
interactions between
electrons make the story somewhat more
complicated but interactions between
electrons are pretty weak they're pretty
weak they're not very strong and for the
most part then they can be ignored
inside a metal for example if the photon
has excess energy it has enough to kick
multiple electrons say it again if a
photon has a lot of energy enough to
excite multiple electrons yeah then and
um what happens do they uh is does one
electron go get extra excited and then
fall back or well any no anything can
happen as long as it's consistent with
the conservation
laws okay but uh typically it's a much
lower probability process to create two
electrons and two holes if it kicked out
two electrons it would make two
holes so that would be a process in
which four particles four
particles were created all
together and that's that's much less
likely
supercite yeah it's it's that's right
it's it's more likely to Super excite
one another another question
photoelectric effect here sort of what
we're talking about is it ever the case
that two photons simultaneously can be
absorbed by an electron that that either
one of them wouldn't do it but both of
them will yeah okay often you need both
of them to conserve both energy and it's
just the probability of
situation is not
prohibition if you have a low energy uh
Photon that's not it doesn't have enough
energy to excite any of the electrons
does it absorb well it it doesn't take
it just takes a tiny tiny bit of energy
to uh to kick it from here to here so
yeah there is some energy which is so
low that it can't do anything it's true
does it does it then not interact or
does it
absorb
well yeah it pretty much just passes
through the system doesn't
uh well that's not really
true
um
uh yeah very low energy po time we'll
find other ways to interact but
uh it'll it'll stop a whole collection
of electrons sling that's a more
complicated
uh but does I
mean you mean that they're actually
moving on the grid back and
forth they actually will be moving on
the grid back and forth yeah space but
space
well but that's that's that's a more
complicated
why did you say electron interact weakly
with each other what say again you said
electron do not interact each other very
strongly but don't they all have the
same negative
charges yeah but they're also they're
also in a background C of positive
charges
uh so the whole thing is electrically
neutral the electrons are interacting
with each other but but uh the electron
interactions are pretty weak partly
they're weak because the electron charge
is screened by uh by the proton charges
but I really didn't want to get into the
electron interaction that's a that's a
separate issue that uh that we Quantum
electr will we talk about that
screening yeah we can talk about it but
not yeah I don't want to talk about that
now yeah yeah screening is an important
phenomenon in particle physics and it
has its analog here but let's come back
to it another time what I really wanted
to get to was the da equation and I have
15 minutes to give you the very very
simplest version of the Der equation
which we will come back to
repeatedly but the very very simplest
version of the dur
equation just a sort of complete a story
here it's obvious you know what story
I'm starting to tell you I'm telling you
the story about
antiparticles okay holes are
antiparticles but what does this what
does this have to do with not a metal in
a box but with a relativistic Quantum
field Theory and the vacuum and
particles and
antiparticles so I want to spend just a
couple of minutes giving you the very
very simplest
version of the's logic
and to keep it really simple let's stay
with one dimension of space okay one
dimension of space in only one
dimension
X we'll come back to more Dimensions
next
time and
um let's write a wave
equation this wave equation is going to
be for a field that I'm going to call S
okay
ah right this electron this is not an
electron it's a neutrino ah I don't know
what it is it's a particle it's a firon
it's a firon but it happens to move with
a speed of light okay it moves with the
speed of light and that means Omega
equals K
right Omega equals K is the relationship
between frequency and wave number or
between energy and momentum this is c =
1 Omega equal
K there's another possibility Omega is
equal to K and what's the other
possibility Omega equals minus K okay
but let's take omega equals
K okay what kind of wave equation does
that correspond
to well that corresponds to the wave
equation DCI by DT
is
equal I think it's
minus DCI by DX this is partial
derivative this is even simpler
than the Schrodinger equation it's ex
why do I say that this is uh that this
is Omega equals K let's imagine the S is
equal to e to the I KX minus Omega t
DCI by d t brings down a factor minus I
Omega DCI by DX brings down a factor i
k if the relation between Omega and K is
just Omega equals K corresponding to Cal
1 then that just says DCI by DT is equal
to minus DC by DX all right so this is a
very very simple wave
equation and it describes waves
which only move in One Direction they
cannot move in both directions they move
only as it to the right or to the
left can you tell if this
uh yeah this these waves move to the
right what would it take to make waves
that move to the
left you want D Side by DT equal plus d
Side by DX
right with either of those two equations
you have particles which move in One
Direction let's say in this case to the
right and let's suppose these are Fons
and and let's even imagine they carry
electric charge so they're electrically
charged
Fons okay now there's something a little
bit crazy about
this Omega equal k
K energy equals momentum can K be
negative sure why not I can write I can
write e to the I
KX and I can also write e to the minus I
KX right I can write both possibilities
things which
are but there's something a little ugly
not ugly a little bit dangerous about
negative values of
K they carry negative values of Omega
and negative values of omega mean
what negative energy all right so this
equation
describes electron electrons
of positive and negative energy let's
just draw a picture Omega equals K
here's Omega equals K Omega versus
K it's just a straight
line for K positive the energy is
positive for K negative the energy is
negative okay this equation simply
describes electrons which can have
either positive or negative
energy uh that sounds like trouble why
is that trouble why is electrons with
negative energy
trouble
well if electrons can have arbitrarily
low momentum remember what happens in in
an
atom uh to an electron which is excited
it radiates and drops down to a lower
state if there were unboundedly low
energies arbitrarily negative then
electrons let's say positive energy
electrons could emit photons and drop
down energy but they wouldn't
necessarily have to stop at zero energy
they could keep dropping down and
dropping down and dropping down and make
arbitrarily negatively energy electrons
while at the same time pumping up the
energy of the electromagnetic field this
sounds very dangerous and it is
dangerous something wrong with this okay
you can't have arbitrarily low energies
well what is the lowest energy
state of the multi-electron
system
doere what the fere what is a fere spere
in this case the phosphere in this case
is start let's suppose we have a zillion
electrons as many as we like and we put
the first electron into the system where
does it
go the it goes down into the lowest
energy state but the lowest energy state
is way the hell down there somewhere off
at minus infinity somewhere the next one
off at minus infinity this is very
dangerous this is a a bad idea what D
said this was this is the simplest
version of Da equation this is a direct
equation in one dimension what D said is
let's pretend that all of the negative
energy states were
filled just like filling the fmis spere
fill all the negative energy
states all the ways up to Zero Energy so
all of these states are
filled there's an electron in every
negative energy
State you can't make a state of lower
energy than that incidentally that's the
lowest possible energy you have you
filled up all the negative energy states
every time you put a negative energy
thing in that lowers the energy you've
put as many negative energy states in as
you can now if I start putting in
positive energy electrons that will
increase the energy so the very lowest
energy State the thing that you could
call a ground
state is to fill it with as many
negative energy electrons as there are
negative energy states
and that's your starting point instead
of a starting point with no electrons
your starting point is fill up
completely the negative energy
C that's the vacuum that's empty space
according to DX Theory thex simple
version start with that since it's the
state of lowest energy let's call it the
vacuum and now what can you do you can
take the only thing you can do is to
take an electron out of the sea the
negative energy C and give it positive
energy so you can take an electron from
over here and put it someplace
else what are the properties of a state
with one electron over here with
positive energy and positive momentum
and one missing electron over
here okay it's a missing
electron well how much how much momentum
does it have incidentally
um it uh
Nega well we remove the negative
negative momentum
electrons yeah so it's zero no no no no
the whole how much how much does the
hole
have is it positive or negative positive
positive positive why is it positive
because it's a missing deficit of
negative momentum all right so what
we've done is create a positive energy a
positive energy
electron and a positive and positive
momentum we've created two positive
momentum objects both moving to the
right uh one with plus charge sorry one
with minus charge the electron with
minus charge and the missing electron
having positive charge negative charge
and positive
charge that uh that in summary and we're
going to do this more completely but
that was D's theory of the electron and
the positron that the positron was
simply a hole in the infinite negative
energy
C he wrote down this equation or the
generalization of it looked at it said I
love that equation but it's got this
terrible disease of having negative
energy states no problem these are
firion you can't put more than one
electron in a negative energy state so
just fill it up completely and call that
empty space having called that empty
space what can you do to it you can
remove one of the negative energy
electrons and put it back as a positive
energy electron sorry put it back yes
put it back as a positive energy
electron that leaves a hole and D said
that hole is a particle of positive uh
charge all right now at first he was
very excited because he thought it was
the
proton it wasn't the proton it's easy to
prove that the mass of the particle here
has to be the same as the mass of the
these are particle and antiparticle this
was the discovery of particles and
antiparticles but this was the basic
logic and it was equations like this
which led to
it notice what a disaster you'd be in if
you tried to describe a bon by this
equation that would be a mad house you
would just keep putting particles into
the negative energy lowest of as many
many as you like and there would be no
ground state there would be no ground
state you could just keep putting in
more and more and more negative energy
bosons so this wave this wave equation
only makes sense for firion would not
make sense for bons and uh that was D's
great discovery that firion can be
described by dur equations like this
that would not make sense for
bans why for just the reasons I
explained
and the idea of
antiparticles um we'll come to anti
particles for bons next time and we'll
discuss the dur equation in more
completeness the real dur equation this
is a Elementary version of
it but uh we'll come to it next time
there's a number of things wrong with
this electron for one thing it only
moves to the right that's crazy for
another thing it's got It's it moves
with the speed of light that's crazy so
there's a number of things that are
wrong with this electron but
uh no it's a
nutrino no it's a nutrino a nutrino is a
ban a neutrino is a ban this is yeah
this is a
nutrino but it's not quite a nutrino
because the nutrino also has
mass for more please visit us at
stanford.edu